<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014, 2015  Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
 - purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
 - copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.
 -
 - THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND ISC DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH
 - REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
 - AND FITNESS.  IN NO EVENT SHALL ISC BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT,
 - INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM
 - LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE
 - OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR
 - PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
-->

<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <xi:include href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This document summarizes changes since the last production release
      of BIND on the corresponding major release branch.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_download">
    <title>Download</title>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/downloads/"
	>http://www.isc.org/downloads/</ulink>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_security">
    <title>Security Fixes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  On servers configured to perform DNSSEC validation using
	  managed trust anchors (i.e., keys configured explicitly
	  via <command>managed-keys</command>, or implicitly 
	  via <command>dnssec-validation auto;</command> or
	  <command>dnssec-lookaside auto;</command>), revoking
	  a trust anchor and sending a new untrusted replacement
	  could cause <command>named</command> to crash with an
	  assertion failure. This could occur in the event of a
	  botched key rollover, or potentially as a result of a
	  deliberate attack if the attacker was in position to
	  monitor the victim's DNS traffic.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This flaw was discovered by Jan-Piet Mens, and is
	  disclosed in CVE-2015-1349. [RT #38344]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A flaw in delegation handling could be exploited to put
	  <command>named</command> into an infinite loop, in which
	  each lookup of a name server triggered additional lookups
	  of more name servers.  This has been addressed by placing
	  limits on the number of levels of recursion
	  <command>named</command> will allow (default 7), and
	  on the number of queries that it will send before
	  terminating a recursive query (default 50).
	</para>
	<para>
	  The recursion depth limit is configured via the
	  <option>max-recursion-depth</option> option, and the query limit
	  via the <option>max-recursion-queries</option> option.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The flaw was discovered by Florian Maury of ANSSI, and is
	  disclosed in CVE-2014-8500. [RT #37580]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_features">
    <title>New Features</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>None</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_changes">
    <title>Feature Changes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          NXDOMAIN responses to queries of type DS are now cached separately
          from those for other types. This helps when using "grafted" zones
          of type forward, for which the parent zone does not contain a
          delegation, such as local top-level domains.  Previously a query
          of type DS for such a zone could cause the zone apex to be cached
          as NXDOMAIN, blocking all subsequent queries.  (Note: This
          change is only helpful when DNSSEC validation is not enabled.
          "Grafted" zones without a delegation in the parent are not a
          recommended configuration.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          NOTIFY messages that are sent because a zone has been updated
          are now given priority above NOTIFY messages that were scheduled
          when the server started up. This should mitigate delays in zone
          propagation when servers are restarted frequently.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Errors reported when running <command>rndc addzone</command>
          (e.g., when a zone file cannot be loaded) have been clarified
          to make it easier to diagnose problems.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added support for OPENPGPKEY type.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When encountering an authoritative name server whose name is
	  an alias pointing to another name, the resolver treats
	  this as an error and skips to the next server. Previously
	  this happened silently; now the error will be logged to
	  the newly-created "cname" log category.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  If named is not configured to validate the answer then
	  allow fallback to plain DNS on timeout even when we know
	  the server supports EDNS.  This will allow the server to
	  potentially resolve signed queries when TCP is being
	  blocked.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_bugs">
    <title>Bug Fixes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  <command>dig</command>, <command>host</command> and
	  <command>nslookup</command> aborted when encountering
	  a name which, after appending search list elements,
	  exceeded 255 bytes. Such names are now skipped, but
	  processing of other names will continue. [RT #36892]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The error message generated when
	  <command>named-checkzone</command> or
	  <command>named-checkconf -z</command> encounters a
	  <option>$TTL</option> directive without a value has
	  been clarified. [RT #37138]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Semicolon characters (;) included in TXT records were
	  incorrectly escaped with a backslash when the record was
	  displayed as text. This is actually only necessary when there
	  are no quotation marks. [RT #37159]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  When files opened for writing by <command>named</command>,
	  such as zone journal files, were referenced more than once
	  in <filename>named.conf</filename>, it could lead to file
	  corruption as multiple threads wrote to the same file. This
	  is now detected when loading <filename>named.conf</filename>
	  and reported as an error. [RT #37172]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>dnssec-keygen -S</command> failed to generate successor
          keys for some algorithm types (including ECDSA and GOST) due to
          a difference in the content of private key files. This has been
          corrected. [RT #37183]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          UPDATE messages that arrived too soon after
          an <command>rndc thaw</command> could be lost. [RT #37233]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Forwarding of UPDATE messages did not work when they were
          signed with SIG(0); they resulted in a BADSIG response code.
          [RT #37216]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When checking for updates to trust anchors listed in
          <option>managed-keys</option>, <command>named</command>
          now revalidates keys based on the current set of
          active trust anchors, without relying on any cached
          record of previous validation. [RT #37506]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  When NXDOMAIN redirection is in use, queries for a name
	  that is present in the redirection zone but a type that
	  is not present will now return NOERROR instead of NXDOMAIN.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  When a zone contained a delegation to an IPv6 name server
	  but not an IPv4 name server, it was possible for a memory
	  reference to be left un-freed. This caused an assertion
	  failure on server shutdown, but was otherwise harmless.
	  [RT #37796]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Due to an inadvertent removal of code in the previous
	  release, when <command>named</command> encountered an
	  authoritative name server which dropped all EDNS queries,
	  it did not always try plain DNS. This has been corrected.
	  [RT #37965]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  A regression caused nsupdate to use the default recursive servers
	  rather than the SOA MNAME server when sending the UPDATE.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Adjusted max-recursion-queries to better accommodate empty
	  caches.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Built-in "empty" zones did not correctly inherit the
	  "allow-transfer" ACL from the options or view. [RT #38310]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A mutex leak was fixed that could cause <command>named</command>
	  processes to grow to very large sizes. [RT #38454]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Fixed some bugs in RFC 5011 trust anchor management,
	  including a memory leak and a possible loss of state
	  information.[RT #38458]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="end_of_life">
    <title>End of Life</title>
    <para>
      The BIND 9.9 (Extended Support Version) will be supported until June, 2017.
      <ulink url="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/"
        >https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_thanks">
    <title>Thank You</title>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/donate/"
	>http://www.isc.org/donate/</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
