<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
        "../../../share/xml/freebsd50.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % release PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//ENTITIES Release Specification//EN" "release.ent">
 %release;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
<info><title>&os; &release.current; Release Notes</title>
  

  <author><orgname>The &os; Project</orgname></author>

  <pubdate>$FreeBSD$</pubdate>

  <copyright>
    <year>2000</year>
    <year>2001</year>
    <year>2002</year>
    <year>2003</year>
    <year>2004</year>
    <year>2005</year>
    <year>2006</year>
    <year>2007</year>
    <year>2008</year>
    <year>2009</year>
    <year>2010</year>
    <year>2011</year>
    <year>2012</year>
    <year>2013</year>
    <holder role="mailto:doc@FreeBSD.org">The &os; Documentation Project</holder>
  </copyright>

  <legalnotice xml:id="trademarks" role="trademarks">
    &tm-attrib.freebsd;
    &tm-attrib.ibm;
    &tm-attrib.ieee;
    &tm-attrib.intel;
    &tm-attrib.sparc;
    &tm-attrib.general;
  </legalnotice>

  <abstract>
    <para>The release notes for &os; &release.current; contain a summary
      of the changes made to the &os; base system on the
      &release.branch; development line.
      This document lists applicable security advisories that were issued since
      the last release, as well as significant changes to the &os;
      kernel and userland.
      Some brief remarks on upgrading are also presented.</para>
  </abstract>
</info>

<sect1 xml:id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This document contains the release notes for &os;
    &release.current;.  It
    describes recently added, changed, or deleted features of &os;.
    It also provides some notes on upgrading
    from previous versions of &os;.</para>

  <para releasetype="current">The &release.type; distribution to which these release notes
    apply represents the latest point along the &release.branch; development
    branch since &release.branch; was created.  Information regarding pre-built, binary
    &release.type; distributions along this branch
    can be found at <uri xlink:href="&release.url;">&release.url;</uri>.</para>

  <para releasetype="snapshot">The &release.type; distribution to which these release notes
    apply represents a point along the &release.branch; development
    branch between &release.prev; and the future &release.next;.
    Information regarding
    pre-built, binary &release.type; distributions along this branch
    can be found at <uri xlink:href="&release.url;">&release.url;</uri>.</para>

  <para releasetype="release">This distribution of &os; &release.current; is a
    &release.type; distribution.  It can be found at <uri xlink:href="&release.url;">&release.url;</uri> or any of its mirrors.  More
    information on obtaining this (or other) &release.type;
    distributions of &os; can be found in the <link xlink:href="&url.books.handbook;/mirrors.html"><quote>Obtaining
    &os;</quote> appendix</link> to the <link xlink:href="&url.books.handbook;/">&os;
    Handbook</link>.</para>

  <para>All users are encouraged to consult the release errata before
    installing &os;.  The errata document is updated with
    <quote>late-breaking</quote> information discovered late in the
    release cycle or after the release.  Typically, it contains
    information on known bugs, security advisories, and corrections to
    documentation.  An up-to-date copy of the errata for &os;
    &release.current; can be found on the &os; Web site.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="new">
  <title>What's New</title>

  <para>This section describes
    the most user-visible new or changed features in &os;
    since &release.prev;.
    In general, changes described here are unique to the &release.branch;
    branch unless specifically marked as &merged; features.
  </para>

  <para>Typical release note items
    document recent security advisories issued after
    &release.prev;,
    new drivers or hardware support, new commands or options,
    major bug fixes, or contributed software upgrades.  They may also
    list changes to major ports/packages or release engineering
    practices.  Clearly the release notes cannot list every single
    change made to &os; between releases; this document focuses
    primarily on security advisories, user-visible changes, and major
    architectural improvements.</para>

  <sect2 xml:id="security">
    <title>Security Advisories</title>

    <para/>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="kernel">
    <title>Kernel Changes</title>

    <para revision="248508">The use of unmapped VMIO buffers eliminates the need to perform
      TLB shootdown for mapping on buffer creation and reuse, greatly reducing the
      amount of IPIs for shootdown on big-SMP machines and eliminating up to 25-30%
      of the system time on i/o intensive workloads.</para>

    <para arch="amd64" revision="254466">The maximum amount of memory the &os; kernel
      can address has been increased from 1TB to 4TB.</para>

    <para>A new &man.cpuset.2; API has been added
      for thread to CPU binding and CPU resource grouping and
      assignment.  The &man.cpuset.1; userland utility has been added
      to allow manipulation of processor sets.</para>

    <para role="merged">The &man.ddb.4; kernel debugger now has an output capture
      facility.  Input and output from &man.ddb.4; can now be captured
      to a memory buffer for later inspection using &man.sysctl.8; or
      a textdump.  The new <command>capture</command> command controls
      this feature.</para>

    <para role="merged">The &man.ddb.4; debugger now supports a simple scripting
      facility, which supports a set of named scripts consisting of a
      set of &man.ddb.4; commands.  These commands can be managed from
      within &man.ddb.4; or with the use of the new &man.ddb.8;
      utility.  More details can be found in the &man.ddb.4; manual
      page.</para>

    <para role="merged">The kernel now supports a new textdump format of kernel
      dumps.  A textdump provides higher-level information via
      mechanically generated/extracted debugging output, rather than a
      simple memory dump.  This facility can be used to generate brief
      kernel bug reports that are rich in debugging information, but
      are not dependent on kernel symbol tables or precisely
      synchronized source code.  More information can be found in the
      &man.textdump.4; manual page.</para>

    <para>Kernel support for M:N threading has been removed.  While
      the KSE (Kernel Scheduled Entities) project was quite successful
      in bringing threading to FreeBSD, the M:N approach taken by the
      KSE library was never developed to its full potential.
      Backwards compatibility for applications using KSE threading
      will be provided via &man.libmap.conf.5; for dynamically linked
      binaries.  The &os; Project greatly appreciates the work of
      &a.julian;, &a.deischen;, and &a.davidxu; on KSE support.</para>

    <para>The &os; kernel now exports information about certain kernel
      features via the <varname>kern.features</varname> sysctl tree.
      The &man.feature.present.3; library call provides a convenient
      interface for user applications to test the presence of
      features.</para>

    <para arch="amd64">The &os; kernel now has support for large
      memory page mappings (<quote>superpages</quote>).</para>

    <para arch="amd64,i386,ia64,powerpc" role="merged">The ULE
      scheduler is now the default process scheduler
      in <filename>GENERIC</filename> kernels.</para>

    <para arch="amd64,i386" revision="240135">Support was added for
      the new Intel on-CPU Bull Mountain random number
      generator, found on IvyBridge and supposedly later CPUs,
      accessible with RDRAND instruction.</para>

    <sect3 xml:id="kernel-virtualization">
      <title>Virtualization support</title>
      <para arch="amd64" revision="245652">The BSD Hypervisor, &man.bhyve.8; is included
        with &os;.  &man.bhyve.8; requires Intel CPUs with VT-x and Extended Page Table (EPT)
        support. These features are on all Nehalem models and beyond
        (e.g. Nehalem and newer), but not on the lower-end Atom CPUs.</para> 
  
      <para revision="227652">&man.virtio.4; support has been added.  &man.virtio.4; is the
        name for the paravirtualization interface developed for the Linux KVM, but
        since adopted to other virtual machine hypervisors (with the notable exception of Xen).
        This work brings in a BSD-licensed clean-room implementation of the virtio kernel drivers
        for disk IO (&man.virtio_blk.4; and &man.virtio_scsi.4;), network IO (&man.vtnet.4;),
        memory ballooning (&man.virtio_balloon.4;), and PCI.
        Tested with on Qemu/KVM, VirtualBox, and &man.bhyve.4;.</para>
  
      <para arch="amd64,i386" revision="255524">Paravirtualized drivers which
        support Microsoft Hyper-V have been imported and made
        part of the amd64 GENERIC kernel.  For i386, these drivers are not part of
        GENERIC, so the following lines must be added to
        <filename>/boot/loader.conf</filename> to load these drivers:
        <programlisting>hv_ata_pci_disengage_load="YES"
hv_netsvc_load="YES"
hv_utils_load="YES"
hv_vmbus_load="YES"</programlisting>  Alternatively, the Hyper-V drivers can be added to the i386
        kernel by adding <literal>device hyperv</literal> to the kernel config, and then
        recompiling the kernel.  Please refer to:
        <link xlink:href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/HyperV">FreeBSD and Microsoft Windows Server Hyper-V support</link>
        for full instructions on how to set up Hyper-V support under FreeBSD.</para>

      <para revision="254738">The &man.vmx.4; driver has been added.
        &man.vmx.4; is a VMware VMXNET3 ethernet driver ported from
        OpenBSD.</para>

      <para revision="255744" arch="amd64,i386">Xen PVHVM virtualization is now
        part of the GENERIC kernel.</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="kernel-arm">
      <title>ARM support</title>

      <para revision="239922">Raspberry PI support has been added.
        Refer to these <link xlink:href="http://kernelnomicon.org/?p=164">setup instructions</link>
        and <link xlink:href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/quick-start-guide">quick start
        guide</link>.</para>
  
      <para revision="253396">The default ABI on ARM is now the ARM EABI. This brings a number of
        improvements and allows future support for VFP and Thumb-2.</para> 
  
      <para revision="239268">ARM support has been greatly improved, including support
        for ARMv6 and ARMv7, SMP and thread-local storage (TLS).
        Additionally support for some newer SoC like the MV78x60 and OMAP4 was added.
        See <link xlink:href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-arm/2012-August/003757.html">this announcement</link>
        for further details.</para>
  
      <para revision="254918">Superpages support on ARM has been added.  Superpages support
        provides improved performance and scalability by allowing TLB
        translations to dynamically cover large physical memory regions.
        All ARMv6 and ARMv7-based platforms can take advantage of this feature.
        See <link xlink:href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/ARMSuperpages">this page</link>
        for further details.</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="boot">
      <title>Boot Loader Changes</title>

      <para arch="amd64,i386" role="merged">The BTX kernel used by the boot
	loader has been changed to invoke BIOS routines from real
	mode.  This change makes it possible to boot &os; from USB
	devices.</para>

      <para arch="amd64,i386" role="merged">A new gptboot boot loader has
        been added to support booting from a GPT labeled disk.  A
        new <command>boot</command> command has been added to
        &man.gpt.8;, which makes a GPT disk bootable by writing the
        required bits of the boot loader, creating a new boot
        partition if required.</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="proc">
      <title>Hardware Support</title>

      <para role="merged">The &man.cmx.4; driver, a driver for Omnikey CardMan 4040
        PCMCIA smartcard readers, has been added.</para>

      <para>The &man.syscons.4; driver now supports Colemak keyboard layout.</para>

      <para role="merged">The &man.uslcom.4; driver, a driver for Silicon
        Laboratories CP2101/CP2102-based USB serial adapters, has been
        imported from OpenBSD.</para>

      <sect4 xml:id="mm">
	<title>Multimedia Support</title>

        <para revision="240609">Support for version 2.0 of the USB Audio reference design
          has been added. New devices should support higher bandwidth,
          increased sampling frequency and wider dynamic range.</para>

      </sect4>

      <sect4 xml:id="net-if">
	<title>Network Interface Support</title>

	<para>The &man.ale.4; driver has been added to provide support
	  for Atheros AR8121/AR8113/AR8114 Gigabit/Fast Ethernet controllers.</para>

	<para>The &man.em.4; driver has been split into two drivers
	  with some common parts.  The &man.em.4; driver will continue
	  to support adapters up to the 82575, as well as new
	  client/desktop adapters.  A new &man.igb.4; driver
	  will support new server adapters.</para>

	<para>The &man.jme.4; driver has been added to provide support
	  for PCIe network adapters based on JMicron JMC250 Gigabit
	  Ethernet and JMC260 Fast Ethernet controllers.</para>

	<para>The &man.malo.4; driver has been added to provide
	  support for Marvell Libertas 88W8335 based PCI network
	  adapters.</para>

	<para>The firmware for the &man.mxge.4; driver has been
	  updated from 1.4.25 to 1.4.29.</para>

	<para>The &man.sf.4; driver has been overhauled to improve its
	  performance and to add support for checksum offloading.  It
	  should also work on all architectures.</para>

	<para>The &man.re.4; driver has been overhauled to fix a
	  number of issues.  This driver now has Wake On LAN (WOL)
	  support.</para>

	<para>The &man.vr.4; driver has been overhauled to fix a
	  number of outstanding issues.  It also now works on all
	  architectures.</para>

	<para arch="amd64,i386" role="merged">The &man.wpi.4; driver has
	  been updated to include a number of stability fixes.</para>

	<para revision="248925">The &man.cxgbe.4; driver has been updated to support
	  40G/10G Ethernet NICs based on Chelsio's Terminator 5 (T5) ASIC.</para>

	<para revision="256694">The iw_cxgbe driver has been added.  This is an
	  experimental iWARP/RDMA driver
	  (kernel verbs only) for Chelsio's T4 and T5 based cards.</para>

	<para revision="255932">The Open Fabrics Enterprise Distribution (OFED) and
	  OFED Infiniband core has been
	  updated to the same version as supplied by Linux version 3.7</para>

	<para revision="255932">The Mellanox Infiniband driver has been updated to firmware
	  version 2.30.3200 for ConnectX3 NICs.  Support has been added for ConnectX3 VPI NICs, where
	  each port can be used as Infiniband 56 GB/s or Ethernet 40 GB/s.  Support has been added
	  for dynamically loading kernel modules for Infiniband core (ibcore) and
	  IP over Infiniband (ipoib).</para>

	<para revision="227614">&man.netmap.4; has been added.  &man.netmap.4; is a framework for
          high-performance direct-to-hardware packet IO, offering low latency and high PPS
          rates to userland applications while bypassing any kernel-side packet processing.
          With &man.netmap.4; it is trivially possible to fully saturate a 10 Gbps network interface with
          minimal packet sizes.  For more information, see:
          <link xlink:href="http://info.iet.unipi.it/~luigi/netmap/">Netmap Project</link>.</para> 

      </sect4>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="net-proto">
      <title>Network Protocols</title>

      <para revision="228571">&man.carp.4; has been rewritten to make addresses
        more sane from the viewpoint of routing daemons such as
        quagga/zebra. It also brings support for a single redundant
        address on the subnet (carpdev), switching state with
        &man.ifconfig.8;, better locking and using modern kernel
        interfaces to allocate multicast memberships.
        Configuration of the CARP protocol via &man.ifconfig.8; has changed, as well as format
	of CARP events submitted to &man.devd.8; has changed. See &man.carp.4;
	for more information. The arpbalance feature of &man.carp.4; is currently
	not supported anymore.</para>

      <para revision="240233">The &man.pf.4; firewall now supports fine-grain locking
        and better utilization on multi-cpu machines resulting in
        significant improvements in performance.</para>

      <para revision="250700">Support for up to 65536 routing tables has been
        introduced.</para>

      <para revision="248552">Support for setting/matching differentiated services
        codepoints (DSCP) in IP header has been added to
        &man.ipfw.8;.</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="disks">
      <title>Disks and Storage</title>

      <para role="merged">The &man.aac.4; driver now supports volumes larger than
        2TB in size.</para>

      <para>The &man.ata.4; driver now supports a spindown command for
        disks; after a configurable amount of time, if no requests
        have been received for a disk, the disk will be spun down
        until the next request.  The &man.atacontrol.8; utility now
        supports a <command>spindown</command> command to configure
        this feature.</para>

      <para role="merged">The &man.hptrr.4; driver has been updated to version 1.2
        from Highpoint.</para>

      <para revision="240616">&man.nvme.4; has been added and provides NVM Express support.
        NVM Express is an optimized register interface, command set and feature set of
        PCI Express (PCIe)-based Solid-State Drives (SSDs).  For more information,
        see <link xlink:href="http://http://www.nvmexpress.org/">nvmexpress.org</link>.</para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 xml:id="fs">
      <title>File Systems</title>

      <para revision="255570">A new kernel-based iSCSI target and initiator has been
        added</para>

      <para revision="243246">UFS filesystems can now be enlarged with &man.growfs.8; while
        mounted read-write. This is especially useful for virtual
        machines, allowing the addition of more harddrive space without
        interruption of service.</para>

      <para revision="241519">A state of the art FUSE implementation is now part of the
        base system. It allows the use of nearly all fusefs file
        systems</para>

      <sect4 xml:id="fs-zfs">
	<title>ZFS</title>

        <para revision="">&man.bsdinstall.8; now supports installing
          ZFS on the root file system.  It includes a single configuration menu
          that allows you to select all of the required details, including
          which drives to use, what ZFS RAID level to use (taking into consideration
          the selected number of drives), GPT or MBR, GELI encryption, forcing 4K sectors,
          pool name, etc.</para>

        <para revision="240868">TRIM support has been added for
          ZFS.</para>

        <para revision="246586">Support for the high performance LZ4 compression algorithm
          has been added to ZFS. LZ4 is usually faster and can achieve a
          higher compression ratio than LZJB, the default compression
          algorithm</para>

        <para revision="252140">Support for L2ARC compression has been added to ZFS.</para>

        <para revision="243524">The zio nop-write improvement from Illumos
          was imported into &os;. To reduce I/O, nop-write skips overwriting
          data if the checksum (cryptographically secure) of new data
          matches the checksum of existing data. It also saves space if
          snapshots are in use.  This improvement only works only on
          datasets with enabled compression, disabled deduplication and
          sha256 checksums.</para>

        <para>ZFS will now compare the checksums of incoming writes to
          the checksum of the existing on-disk data and avoid issuing any
          write I/O for data that has not changed. This will reduce I/O
          as well as space usage because if the old block is referenced
          by a snapshot, both copies of the block are kept even though
          both contain the same data.</para>

      </sect4>

    </sect3>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="userland">
    <title>Userland Changes</title>

   <para revision="255321">On platforms where &man.clang.1; is the default
      system compiler, (such as i386, amd64, arm) GCC and GNU libstdc++ are no
      longer built by default.  &man.clang.1; and libc++ from LLVM are used on
      these platforms by instead.  GCC 4.2.1 and libstdc++ are still built
      and used by default on pc98 and all other platforms where &man.clang.1;
      is not the default system compiler.
   </para>

   <para revision="251662">&man.clang.1; and llvm have been updated to
     version 3.3 release.  Please refer to
     <link xlink:href="http://llvm.org/releases/3.3/tools/clang/docs/ReleaseNotes.html">
     Clang 3.3 Release Notes.</link></para>

    <para role="merged" revision="255949">BIND has been replaced by &man.unbound.8; for
      local dns resolution in the base system.  With this change, nslookup
      and dig are no longer a part of the base system.  Users should
      instead use &man.host.1; and &man.drill.1; Alternatively,
      nslookup and dig can be obtained by installing the
      dns/bind-tools port.</para>

    <para revision="225937">sysinstall has been removed from the base system.
      Auxiliary libraries and tools used by sysinstall such as libdisk, libftpio,
      and sade have also been removed.  sysinstall has been replaced by
      &man.bsdinstall.8; and &man.bsdconfig.8;.</para>

    <para revision="256106">&man.freebsd-version.1; has been added.  This tool
      makes a best effort to determine the version and patch level of
      the installed kernel and userland.</para>

    <para revision="255191">GNU patch has been removed from the base system, and replaced
      by a BSD-licensed &man.patch.1; program.</para>

    <para revision="241511">GNU sort has been removed from the base system, and replaced
      by a BSD-licensed &man.sort.1; program.</para>

    <para revision="235723">Berkely yacc (byacc) has been imported
      from <link xlink:href="http://invisible-island.net/byacc/">invisible island</link>.
      This brings bison compatibilities to &man.yacc.1; while preserving full
      backwards compatibility with previous version of &man.yacc.1;.</para>

    <para revision="250881">&man.lex.1; has been replaced by flex 2.5.37</para>

    <para revision="250699">&man.make.1; has been replaced with the 
      "Portable" BSD make tool (bmake) from NetBSD.</para>

    <para role="merged">The &man.adduser.8; utility now supports
      a <option>-M</option> option to set the mode of a new user's
      home directory.</para>

    <para>BSD-licensed versions of &man.ar.1; and &man.ranlib.1;,
      based on <filename>libarchive</filename>, have replaced the GNU
      Binutils versions of these utilities.</para>

    <para>BSD-licensed versions of &man.bc.1; and &man.dc.1; have
      replaced their GNU counterparts.</para>

    <para role="merged">&man.chflags.1; now supports a <option>-v</option> flag for
      verbose output and a <option>-f</option> flag to ignore errors
      with the same semantics as (for example)
      &man.chmod.1;.</para>

    <para>For compatibility with other implementations, &man.cp.1; now
      supports a <option>-a</option> flag, which is equivalent to
      specifying the <option>-RrP</option> flags.</para>

    <para>BSD-licensed version of &man.cpio.1; based on
      <filename>libarchive</filename>, has replaced the GNU cpio.
      Note that the GNU cpio is still installed as
      <filename>gcpio</filename>.</para>

    <para>The &man.env.1; program now supports <option>-u
      <replaceable>name</replaceable></option>
      which will completely unset the given variable
      <replaceable>name</replaceable> by removing it from the environment,
      instead of just setting it to a null value.</para>

    <para>The &man.fdopendir.3; library function has been added.</para>

    <para role="merged">The &man.fetch.3; library now support HTTP 1.1
      If-Modified-Since behavior.  The &man.fetch.1; program now
      supports <option>-i <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option>
      which will only download the specified HTTP URL if the content
      is newer than <replaceable>filename</replaceable>.</para>

    <para>&man.find.1; has been enhanced by the addition of a number
      of primaries that were present in GNU find but not &os;
      &man.find.1;.</para>

    <para>&man.kgdb.1; now supports a new <command>add-kld</command>
      command to make it easier to debug crash dumps with kernel
      modules.</para>

    <para>The &man.ls.1; program now supports a <option>-D</option>
      option to specify a date format string to be used with the long
      format (<option>-l</option>) output.</para>

    <para>&man.nc.1; now supports a <option>-O</option> switch to
      disable the use of TCP options.</para>

    <para>&man.nc.1;'s <option>-o</option> switch has been deprecated.
      It will be removed in a future release.</para>

    <para>The &man.ping6.8; utility now returns <literal>2</literal>
      when the packet transmission was successful but no responses
      were received (this is the same behavior as &man.ping.8;).
      It returned a non-zero value before this change.</para>

    <para>The &man.procstat.1; utility has been added to display
      detailed information about processes.</para>

    <para role="merged">The &man.realpath.1; utility now supports
      a <option>-q</option> flag to suppress warnings; it now also
      accepts multiple paths on its command line.</para>

    <para>&man.sh.1; has many bug fixes, some new features, and will now
      refuse to parse some invalid scripts.  Additionally, it now
      has filename completion and defaults to the &quot;emacs&quot; editing
      mode.</para>

    <para>The &man.split.1; utility now supports a <option>-n</option>
      flag to split a file into a certain number of chunks.</para>

    <para>The &man.tar.1; utility now supports a <option>-Z</option>
      flag to enable &man.compress.1;-style
      compression/decompression.</para>

    <para>The &man.tar.1; utility now supports a
      <option>--numeric-owner</option> flag to ignore user/group names
      on create and extract.</para>

    <para>The &man.tar.1; utility now supports an
      <option>-S</option> flag to sparsify files on extraction.</para>

    <para>The &man.tar.1; utility now supports a <option>-s</option>
      flag to substitute filenames based on the specified regular
      expression.</para>

    <para>The &man.tcgetsid.3; library function has been added to
      return the process group ID for the session leader for the
      controlling terminal.  It is defined in IEEE Std 1003.1-2001
      (POSIX).</para>

    <para>&man.top.1; now supports a <option>-P</option> flag to
      provide per-CPU usage statistics.</para>

    <para>&man.zdump.8; is now working properly on 64 bit architectures.
      </para>

    <para>&man.traceroute.8; now has the ability to print the AS
      number for each hop with the new <option>-a</option> switch; a
      new <option>-A</option> option allows selecting a particular
      WHOIS server.</para>

    <para>&man.traceroute6.8; now supports a <option>-U</option> flag
      to send probe packets with no upper-layer protocol, rather than
      the usual UDP probe packets.</para>

    <sect3 xml:id="rc-scripts">
      <title><filename>/etc/rc.d</filename> Scripts</title>

      <para/>

    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="contrib">
    <title>Contributed Software</title>

    <para revision="251300">&man.jemalloc.3; has been updated to 3.4.0.
      See <link xlink:href="http://www.facebook.com/jemalloc/">this link</link>.
      for more details.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>AMD</application> has been updated from 6.0.10
      to 6.1.5.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>awk</application> has been updated from 1 May
      2007 release to the 23 October 2007 release.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>bzip2</application> has been updated from 1.0.4
      to 1.0.5.</para>

    <para revision="251794"><application>CVS</application> has been removed from the
    base system, but is still available from ports</para>

    <para revision="251886">Subversion has been imported into the base system and
      is installed as <application>svnlite</application>.  <application>svnlite</application>
      should only be used for checking out &os; source and committing, and does not
      replace the full Subversion port.</para>

    <para revision="234449"><application>file</application> has been updated to 5.11.</para>

    <para revision="252726"><application>hostapd</application> has been
      updated from 0.5.8 to 0.5.10.</para>

    <para><application>IPFilter</application> has been updated to 5.1.2.</para>

    <para revision="250592"><application>less</application> has been updated to
      v458.</para>

    <para><application>ncurses</application> has been updated from
      to 5.7-20081102.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>OpenSSH</application> has been updated
      to 6.4.</para>

    <para revision="236109"><application>OpenPAM</application> has been updated to
      the Micrampelis release.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>sendmail</application> has been updated from
      8.14.1 to 8.14.7.</para>

    <para role="merged">The timezone database has been updated from
      the <application>tzdata2008h</application> release to
      the <application>tzdata2009m</application> release.</para>

    <para>The stdtime part of libc, &man.zdump.8; and &man.zic.8;
      have been updated from the <application>tzcode2004a</application>
      release to the <application>tzcode2009h</application> release.
      If you have upgraded from source or via the &man.freebsd-update.8;,
      then please run &man.tzsetup.8; to install a new /etc/localtime.
      </para>

    <para revision="252726"><application>WPA Supplicant</application> has been
      updated to 2.0.</para>

    <para role="merged"><application>xz</application> has been updated
      from snapshot as of 12 April 2010 to 5.0.0.</para>

    <para revision="258231" role="merged">&man.nvi.1; has been updated to 2.1.2.</para>

    <para revision="254225">&man.nvi.1; supports wide character locales.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="ports">
    <title>Ports/Packages Collection Infrastructure</title>

    <para revision="257444">The pkg_add, pkg_create, pkg_delete, pkg_info,
      pkg_updating, and pkg_version utilities have been removed.
      &man.pkg.7; must now be used to install binary packages.  &man.pkg.7;
      is the next generation &os; package manager, also referred to as "pkgng".</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="releng">
    <title>Release Engineering and Integration</title>

    <para role="merged">The supported version of
      the <application>GNOME</application> desktop environment
      (<package>x11/gnome2</package>) has been
      updated from 2.20.1 to 2.22.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="doc">
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para/>

  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="upgrade">
  <title>Upgrading from previous releases of &os;</title>

  <para arch="amd64,i386">Binary upgrades between RELEASE versions
    (and snapshots of the various security branches) are supported
    using the &man.freebsd-update.8; utility.  The binary upgrade
    procedure will update unmodified userland utilities, as well as
    unmodified GENERIC kernels distributed as a part of an official
    &os; release.  The &man.freebsd-update.8; utility requires that
    the host being upgraded have Internet connectivity.</para>

  <para>Source-based upgrades (those based on recompiling the &os;
    base system from source code) from previous versions are
    supported, according to the instructions in
    <filename>/usr/src/UPDATING</filename>.</para>

  <important>
    <para>Upgrading &os; should only be attempted after
      backing up <emphasis>all</emphasis> data and configuration
      files.</para>
  </important>
</sect1>
</article>
