<!--
     The FreeBSD Documentation Project
     The FreeBSD French Documentation Project

     $Id$
     $FreeBSD$
     Original revision: 1.12
     Ce fichier contient les instructions pour l'installation
     specifique aux systemes sparc64.

-->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <title>***Non traduit***Installing &os;</title>

  <para>This text describes how to install and boot the &arch; port.
    Users of this port are encouraged to subscribe to the
    &a.sparc;.</para>

  <warning>
    <para>The kernel and userland binaries mentioned below are highly
      experimental (for example, the kernel contains some ATA changes
      and EEPROM handling code which could potentially be dangerous).
      Unless you know what you are doing and are willing to cope with
      any damage that might arise, you should probably not be trying
      this.</para>
  </warning>

  <para>Unlike &os;/i386 or &os;/alpha, there is no version of
    &man.sysinstall.8; for &os;/&arch;.  The installation procedure
    consists of loading a kernel (either from CDROM or the network)
    onto the &arch; machine, with a root filesystem on CDROM or
    exported via NFS.  The utilities on the root filesystem can then
    be used to partition the local disk on the &arch; machine and
    optionally to copy the &os; distribution to the local disk to make
    a stand-alone machine.</para>

  <para>Currently, there are two ways to install &os;/&arch; on a new
    machine.  By far the easier of the two is to install from CDROM;
    this method allows you to install &os; without any dependencies on
    any other computers.</para>

  <para>If installing from CDROM is impossible or undesirable, the
    alternative is to install over the network.  This requires another
    machine, suitably configured, to serve the boot loader, kernel,
    and root filesystem to the new machine, via a combination of
    RARP, TFTP, and either BOOTP or DHCP.  This netboot server can be
    another &os; machine, but is not required to be.</para>

  <para>You will need to decide which of these methods you want to use
    for installation, as this will determine the set of files you need
    to download (if any), as well as the steps required to do the
    installation.</para>

<!-- this should read "in this document" after the re-structure -->

  <important>
    <para>The URLs in this section are provisional and subject to
      change.  Please see the archives of the &a.sparc; for the most
      recent locations of files.  This notice will be removed when
      more permanent URLs have been determined.</para>
  </important>

  <sect2 xml:id="getting-to-prom-prompt">
    <title>Getting to the PROM Prompt</title>

    <para>Most &arch; systems are set up to boot automatically from
      disk.  To install &os;, you need to boot over the network or
      from a CDROM, which requires you to break into the PROM
      (OpenFirmware).</para>

    <para>To do this, reboot the system, and wait until the boot
      message appears.  It depends on the model, but should look about
      like:</para>

    <screen>Sun Blade 100 (UltraSPARC-IIe), Keyboard Present
Copyright 1998-2001 Sun Microsystems, Inc.  All rights reserved.
OpenBoot 4.2, 128 MB memory installed, Serial #51090132.
Ethernet address 0:3:ba:b:92:d4, Host ID: 830b92d4.</screen>

    <para>If your system proceeds to boot from disk at this point, you
      need to press <keycombo action="simul"><keycap>L1</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
      or <keycombo action="simul"><keycap>Stop</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
      on the keyboard, or send a <command>BREAK</command> over the
      serial console (using for example <command>~#</command> in
      &man.tip.1; or &man.cu.1;) to get to the PROM prompt.  It looks
      like this:</para>

    <screenco>
      <areaspec>
	<area xml:id="prompt-single" coords="1 5"/>
	<area xml:id="prompt-smp" coords="2 5"/>
      </areaspec>

      <screen><prompt>ok     </prompt>
<prompt>ok {0} </prompt></screen>

      <calloutlist>
	<callout arearefs="prompt-single">
	  <para>This is the prompt used on systems with just one
	    CPU.</para>
	</callout>

	<callout arearefs="prompt-smp">
	  <para>This is the prompt used on SMP systems, the digit
	    indicates the number of the active CPU.</para>
	</callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </screenco>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="prepare-cd">
    <title>Preparing for a CDROM Installation</title>

    <para>If you want to do a CDROM installation, an ISO image with a
      snapshot of &os;/&arch; can be found at <uri xlink:href="&release.url;">&release.url;</uri>.  This file can be used to create a
      bootable CDROM which contains everything necessary to boot and
      load at least a minimal &os; installation.</para>

<!-- XXX ISO location?-->
    <para>Place the CDROM into your drive, and break into the PROM as
      described above.  On the PROM prompt, type <command>boot
      cdrom</command>.  The system should boot into single-user mode
      now, and you can create the disk label and install the base
      system archive as described in <xref linkend="creating-disk-label"/> and <xref linkend="creating-root-filesystem"/>.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="prepare-network">
    <title>Preparing for a Network Installation</title>

    <para>A &os;/&arch; kernel is booted by having the firmware
      retrieve and execute a <application>loader</application>, which
      in turn fetches and executes the actual kernel.  For this boot
      process, you need to set up &man.rarpd.8; and &man.tftpd.8; (for
      the firmware) and &man.bootpd.8; (for the
      <application>loader</application>) on another networked system.
      The loader can fetch a kernel using TFTP or NFS.  All of this is
      covered in detail below.</para>

    <sect3 xml:id="downloading">
      <title>Getting the Required Files</title>

      <para>For a network installation, you will need several files.
	First, you will need to download a &os;/&arch; loader for
	&man.tftpd.8; to serve to your &arch; client.  The loader will
	use either TFTP or NFS to retrieve the &os; kernel from the
	netboot server.  There is a separate loader for each of these
	methods (i.e. a loader for TFTP and a loader for NFS).  You
	should download one of the following files, as
	appropriate:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><uri xlink:href="&release.url;loader-tftp.gz">&release.url;loader-tftp.gz</uri></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><uri xlink:href="&release.url;loader-nfs.gz">&release.url;loader-nfs.gz</uri></para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A network installation also requires a kernel to be served
	to the netboot client.  A suitable kernel can be found at
	<uri xlink:href="&release.url;">&release.url;</uri>.</para>
<!-- XXX kernel filename?-->

      <para>Finally, you will need a &man.tar.1; archive which
	contains the binaries and configuration files from the base
	system.  This file is available from <uri xlink:href="&release.url;distrib.tar.gz">&release.url;distrib.tar.gz</uri>.</para>
    </sect3>

<!-- put the words "netboot server" in here -->
    <sect3>
      <title>rarpd</title>

      <para>You need to add the Ethernet address of your &os;/&arch;
	system to <filename>/etc/ethers</filename> on the netboot
	server.  An entry looks like:</para>

      <programlisting>0:3:ba:b:92:d4 your.host.name</programlisting>

      <para>The Ethernet address is usually displayed in the boot
	message.</para>

      <para>Make sure <systemitem>your.host.name</systemitem> is in
	<filename>/etc/hosts</filename> or has a valid DNS entry (or
	use an IP address).  Then, start &man.rarpd.8; on a network
	interface that is on the same subnet as the &os;/&arch;
	system.</para>
    </sect3>

<!-- put the words "netboot server" in here -->
    <sect3>
      <title>tftpd</title>

      <para>Activate &man.tftpd.8; in your &man.inetd.8;
	configuration by uncommenting the following line in
	<filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>tftp dgram udp  wait nobody /usr/libexec/tftpd tftpd /tftpboot</programlisting>

      <para>Copy the unpacked loader to your
	<filename>/tftpboot</filename> directory, and name it with the
	&os;/&arch; host's IP address in upper-case hexadecimal
	notation without dots (or use appropriately-named symbolic
	links).  For example, your setup may look like this, for an IP
	address of <systemitem>192.168.0.16</systemitem>:</para>

      <screen>  lrwx------  1 tmm users       9 Jul 24 17:05 /tftpboot/C0A80010 -&gt; boot/loader
  -rw-r--r--  1 tmm users 1643021 Oct 20 18:04 /tftpboot/boot/loader</screen>

      <para>If you have trouble booting, it is very helpful to use
	&man.tcpdump.1; to monitor the TFTP requests.  This will allow
	you to see the file name you need to use for the loader.
	Error replies by the TFTP server are most often due to
	incorrect file permissions.</para>
    </sect3>

<!-- put the words "netboot server" in here -->
    <sect3>
      <title>Setting up bootpd/dhcpd</title>

      <para>You can use either BOOTP or DHCP (both not both) to
	provide some parameters to the boot loader, such as a
	machine's IP address.  If you are using another &os; machine
	as a netboot server, the BOOTP functionality is provided by
	&man.bootpd.8;, which is a part of the &os; base system.
	Several DHCP servers are provided in the &os; Ports
	Collection.</para>

      <para>If you are going to use &man.bootpd.8;, create entries for
	your &os;/&arch; system in the server's
	<filename>/etc/bootptab</filename> (see &man.bootptab.5; for
	more details):</para>

      <programlisting>.default:\
  :bf="kernel":dn=local:ds=<replaceable>name-server-ip-address</replaceable>:\
  :gw=<replaceable>gateway-ip-address</replaceable>:ht=ether:hd="/tftpboot/boot/kernel":hn:\
  :sa="<replaceable>tftp-server-ip-address</replaceable>":\
  :rp="<replaceable>tftp-server-ip-address</replaceable>:<replaceable>nfs-root-directory</replaceable>":\
  :sm=<replaceable>ip-netmask</replaceable>

<replaceable>name-of-the-entry</replaceable>:\
  ha=<replaceable>sparc64-ethernet-address</replaceable>:ip=<replaceable>sparc64-ip-address</replaceable>:tc=.default</programlisting>

      <para>The Ethernet address must be the same as the one in the
	TFTP example above, but it is specified hexadecimal notation
	without colons (for the example above, this would be
	<literal>0003ba0b92d4</literal>).  NFS/TFTP specific entries
	can be omitted if the given method is not used.  The strings
	given in the <literal>hd</literal> and <literal>bf</literal>
	properties are concatenated to give the boot file name.  If
	your kernel is named differently or you use another directory,
	change these values as required.  If you are booting using
	NFS, remove the <literal>bf</literal> and
	<literal>hd</literal> settings (or change them to specify the
	directory and file inside the NFS root hierarchy in which the
	kernel will reside).  The name of the host entry is
	conventionally the host name without the domain
	appended.</para>

      <para>For a DHCP server, add an entry similar to the following
	to your <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename> file.  An example
	entry for <application>ISC DHCP</application> version 2
	(available in the &os; Ports Collection as <package>net/isc-dhcp2</package>) is shown
	below:</para>

      <programlisting>host <replaceable>name-of-entry</replaceable> {
  hardware ethernet <replaceable>sparc64-ethernet-address</replaceable>;
  option host-name "<replaceable>sparc64-fully-qualified-domain-name</replaceable>";
  fixed-address <replaceable>sparc64-ip-address</replaceable>;
  always-reply-rfc1048 on;
  filename "kernel";
  option root-path "<replaceable>tftp-server-ip-address</replaceable>:<replaceable>nfs-root-directory</replaceable>";
}</programlisting>

      <para>The <literal>filename</literal> option corresponds to the
	concatenation of <literal>hd</literal> and
	<literal>bf</literal> in <filename>/etc/bootptab</filename>.
	The Ethernet address is specified in hexadecimal with colons,
	just like in the &man.rarpd.8; example above.
	<literal>options root-path</literal> corresponds to
	<literal>rp</literal> in <filename>/etc/bootptab</filename>.
	If the name given in <literal>option host-name</literal> is
	resolvable, i.e. has a DNS entry or is associated with an
	address in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>, the
	<literal>fixed-address</literal> specification can be
	omitted.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Loading the Kernel</title>

      <para>With the daemons on the netboot server configured, the
	next step is to copy the kernel (obtained during the steps of
	<xref linkend="downloading"/>) to an appropriate directory.
	There are two ways of retrieving a kernel over the network:
	TFTP and NFS.  (You specified one of these two alternatives by
	picking a loader.)</para>

      <para>For both TFTP and NFS, the loader will use the parameters
	that it obtained via BOOTP or DHCP to find the kernel.</para>

      <sect4>
	<title>Loading the Kernel over TFTP</title>

	<para>Place the kernel in the directory you specified using
	  <literal>bf</literal> and <literal>hd</literal> in the
	  <filename>/etc/bootptab</filename> or the
	  <literal>filename</literal> parameter to
	  <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename>.</para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4>
	<title>Loading the Kernel over NFS</title>

	<para>Export the directory that was specified by the
	  <literal>rp</literal> property in
	  <filename>/etc/bootptab</filename> or the
	  <literal>root-path</literal> parameter in
	  <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename> (see &man.exports.5;).  Copy
	  the kernel to the directory you specified using
	  <literal>bf</literal> and <literal>hd</literal> in the
	  <filename>/etc/bootptab</filename> or the
	  <literal>filename</literal> parameter to
	  <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename>.</para>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Loading the Base System to the Netboot Server</title>

      <para>You must extract the base system distribution image to the
	NFS root directory specified either by the
	<literal>rp</literal> option in
	<filename>/etc/bootptab</filename> or the
	<literal>root-path</literal> option in
	<filename>dhcpd.conf</filename>.  This directory tree will
	become the &arch;'s root filesystem once the kernel is booted.
	Besides providing a normal userland environment, it also
	contains all of the necessary utilities for you to install the
	distribution on the &arch; client's local disk.</para>

      <para>Using whatever editing tools you have on the netboot
	server, you probably will want to edit the &arch;'s
	<filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and
	<filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename> and set a
	<systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> password.</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Booting</title>

      <para>If all goes well, you can now boot the &os; on your &arch;
	machine by dropping into the PROM prompt as described in <xref linkend="getting-to-prom-prompt"/>.  Now, just type
	<command>boot net</command> and the system should boot.
	Specifically, the loader is retrieved via TFTP, it then does a
	BOOTP request and will proceed to load the kernel (either
	using TFTP or NFS, depending on your choice of loader).  Then,
	it should wait 10 seconds for user input and proceed to
	execute the kernel.</para>

      <para>If something does not work in between, and you suspect
	TFTP/NFS/BOOTP problems, <application>Ethereal</application>
	(available in the &os; Ports Collection as <package> net/ethereal</package>) is usually helpful.
	The most common problems are related to bad file permissions.
	Also note that &man.rarpd.8; will not answer to packets under
	some circumstances, refer to the manual page for
	details.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="creating-disk-label">
    <title>Creating a Disk Label</title>

    <para>The kernel supports the Sun disk label format, so you can
      label the disks you want to use with &os; from Solaris.</para>

    <para>&os; disk labels must currently be created by hand, as
      &man.sysinstall.8; is not yet available on &os;/&arch;.  Please
      refer to the <link xlink:href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/">FreeBSD
      Handbook</link> for more information about labels and special
      partitions.</para>

    <para>On &os;/&arch;, a Sun compatibility label is embedded in the
      &os; label; this is needed for the PROM to boot from disk.  This
      imposes an additional restriction on the disk label format:
      partitions are required to start on a cylinder boundary.</para>

    <para>To create a disk label, the following procedure is the
      easiest:</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
	<para>Run <command>disklabel -w -r
	  device auto</command> to create a
	  basic disk label.  The third argument you need specify here
	  is just the name of the device, not the complete path to the
	  device node (e.g. <filename>ad0</filename> for the first
	  ATA disk).</para>
      </step>

      <step>
	<para> Use <command>disklabel -e
	  device</command> to open an
	  editor in which you can edit the disk label.  The
	  information presented to you should look like:</para>

	<screen># /dev/ad6c:
type: unknown
disk: amnesiac
label:
flags:
bytes/sector: 512
sectors/track: 63
tracks/cylinder: 16
sectors/cylinder: 1008
cylinders: 79780
sectors/unit: 80418240
rpm: 3600
interleave: 1
trackskew: 0
cylinderskew: 0
headswitch: 0           # milliseconds
track-to-track seek: 0  # milliseconds
drivedata: 0

8 partitions:
#        size   offset    fstype   [fsize bsize bps/cpg]
  c: 80418240        0    unused        0     0         # (Cyl.    0 - 79779)</screen>

	<para>You can now add new partitions in the same format as the
	  already present line.  Using <literal>*</literal> in the
	  offset field makes the procedure easier; please refer to the
	  &man.disklabel.8; manual page for more information.</para>

	<para>To make sure the restriction mentioned above is met, the
	  size of each partition must be a multiple of the number of
	  sectors per cylinder as shown in the information that is
	  presented in the editor (1008 in the example above).</para>

	<para>When you are done, save your changes and quit the
	  editor.i This will cause the disk label to be
	  written.</para>

	<warning>
	  <para>This procedure will overwrite any disk label that may
	    be already present on the disk.  Any existing filesystems
	    on this disk must have their respective partition entries
	    in the old and new label match
	    <emphasis>exactly</emphasis>, or they will be
	    lost.</para>
	</warning>

	<para>If you want to double-check that your partitions end on
	  cylinder boundaries, run <command>disklabel -e
	  device</command> again.  The
	  editor will display the cylinders used by a particular
	  partition on the right hand side of the output.  If any of
	  the partitions you defined (i.e. anything except partition
	  <literal>c</literal>) shows an <literal>*</literal> next to
	  it, the partition does <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> start or end
	  on a cylinder boundary.  You <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> fix
	  these or your system will not work.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
	<para>Use <command>disklabel -B</command> if you want to make
	  the disk bootable for &os;/&arch;.</para>

	<warning>
	  <para>Using <command>disklabel -B</command> on a disk will
	    overwrite any preexisting boot block, so it will likely
	    render any other operating system installed on the same
	    disk unbootable.</para>
	</warning>

	<para>If you do not want to overwrite the boot block, it is
	  possible to load the <application>loader</application> via
	  TFTP as described above, but have it boot the kernel from
	  disk.  This requires a special loader binary, which is
	  available at <uri xlink:href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/development/sparc64/loader-ufs.gz">ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/development/sparc64/loader-ufs.gz</uri></para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="creating-root-filesystem">
    <title>Creating the Root Fileystem</title>

    <para>If you want to boot from a local disk, you will need to
      create a root filesystem to hold the base system binaries and
      configuration files (and optionally other filesystems mounted
      in places such as <filename>/usr</filename> and
      <filename>/var</filename>).</para>

    <para>The kernel contains support for Sun disklabels, so you can
      use Solaris disks, which may even be prepared using
      <application>newfs</application> under Solaris.  NetBSD disk
      labels and filesystems are also usable from &os;.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> run Solaris
	<application>fsck</application> on filesystems modified by
	&os;.  Doing so will damage the file permissions.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>To create filesystems and to install the base system, boot
      from CDROM or via NFS and create a disk label as described in
      <xref linkend="creating-disk-label"/>.</para>

    <para>When booting the first time and you have not entered your
      root partition into <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> yet, you may
      need to specify your root partition on the mountroot prompt when
      booting (use a format like
      <command>ufs:diskpartition</command>,
      i.e. leave the slice specification out).  If the kernel does
      automatically attempt to boot from another filesystem, press a
      key other than <keycap>Enter</keycap> on the
      <application>loader</application> prompt:</para>

    <screen>Hit [Enter] to boot immediately, or any other key for command prompt.</screen>

    <para>Then, boot the kernel using <command>boot -a -s</command>,
      which will cause the kernel to ask you for the root partition
      and then boot into single-user mode.  Once the root filesystem
      has been entered into <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>, it should
      be automatically mounted as <filename>/</filename> on the next
      boot.</para>

    <para>If you are booting over the network (via NFS), the above
      BOOTP entries should suffice to have the kernel find and mount
      the root filesystem via NFS.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="installing-base-system">
    <title>Installing the Base System</title>

    <para>If you booted the kernel from the network, you downloaded a
      &man.tar.1; archive with the base system and exported it from
      the netboot server via NFS.  You can unpack this same archive to
      your local disk to create a stand-alone system (remember to copy
      the kernel over as well).</para>

    <para>If you booted from CDROM, the same archive is available in
      <filename>/root/</filename> on the CDROM.</para>

    <para>Before booting the system stand-alone, you will want to edit
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and
      <filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename> and set a
      <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> password.</para>

    <para>Note that some programs from the base system may not be
      present in the archive, or may not work properly yet.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
